Guide to the Paul Alexander Baran Papers SC1234
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Paul Alexander Baran papers
1928-1964
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Baran, Paul A.
SC1234
9 Linear Feet
Correspondence, writings and audio recordings of Paul A. Baran.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Alexander Baran was a professor of economics at Stanford from 1949 until his death of a heart attack in 1964. His most important works were The Political Economy of Growth (1957), and Monopoly Capital (1965), co-authored with Paul M. Sweezy. Paul Baran was an expert in comparative economic systems (capitalism and socialism), and considered himself a Marxist.
Born in Nikolaev, Russia, in 1909, Baran received his education in Germany, obtaining a Ph. D. in economics from the University of Berlin in 1931. Having to leave Germany with the rise of Hitler, Baran spent a brief time in the Soviet Union, and then some years in France, Poland, and Britain, working for his family's timber business. He then emigrated to the United States in 1938, and served in the U.S. Army during the second world war as an expert on Russian and German economics. After the war, Baran worked as an economist at the Federal Reserve Bank, and after being invited to Stanford as a visiting lecturer in the summer of 1948, was hired as an associate professor, and granted tenure in 1951. Baran became quite a controversial figure at Stanford after expressing his support for the Cuban Revolution in 1959. He remained one of the economics department's most popular professors until his death in 1964.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology
1909-08-25 Paul Alexander Baran (PAB) is born in Nikolaev, Ukraine. On all official documents, PAB's birthday is the above date, but he maintained that this was an error, and that his real birthday was December 8, 1910, which is the date he and his family celebrated.
1926 Baran graduates from German Gymnasium in Dresden, to where he had moved with his parents in 1921, and returns to USSR, where he enrolls in the Plekhanov (Karl Marx) Institute of Economics at the University of Moscow.
1928-1932 Baran returns to Germany, completes his graduate studies in Berlin, Breslau, and Frankfurt's Institute for Social Research, writes for Rudolf Hilferding's "Die Gesellschaft" under the pen name "Alexander Gabriel." Earns Diplom Volkswirt (Master's Degree in Political Economy) and Dr. Phil. from Friedrich Wilhelm University in Berlin.
1934-1935 Baran returns to USSR to visit his parents, but after several months, leaves for Vilna, Poland, where he has relatives, due to political situation in USSR.
1935-1938 Baran works for his uncles' timber business in Vilna, and eventually moves to London as the company's representative.
1939 Baran moves to the U.S., with the intention of pursuing an academic career in economics, as Germany occupies Poland. Meets Paul Sweezy in Cambridge. Enrolls at Harvard as graduate student in economics.
1941 Baran receives an M.A. in economics from Harvard. He had obtained a Ph.D. (Dr. Phil.) at the University of Berlin, but felt he needed to update and augment both his education and his credentials with a degree from Harvard.
1941-1942 Baran accepts research fellowship working on problems of price controls at the Brookings Institution.
1942-1945 After working briefly at the Office of Price Administration, Baran joins the Office of Strategic Services (OSS), working under E.S. Mason, and is drafted into the Army and reassigned to the OSS. His final rank was Technical Sergeant.
1945 PAB works for the United States Strategic Bombing Survey (USSBS) under direction of J.K. Galbraith. (For an entertaining account of PAB's stint with the USSBS while on assignment in Germany, see J.K. Galbraith's memoir, A Life in Our Times, 1981.)
1946-1949 Baran works briefly at Department of Commerce and then about 3 years at the Federal Reserve Bank in New York. First saved letters of correspondence between PMS and PAB are from 1949 when he lived in New York.
1949 After having taught a seminar during summer quarter at Stanford as a visiting scholar in 1948, Stanford hires Baran as an associate professor
1951 Stanford promotes Baran to full professor with tenure.
1952 "National Economic Planning" published (see bibliography)
1953 Baran spends fall semester at Oxford University, where he delivered a series of lectures forming the basis of his book, Political Economy of Growth.
1955 Baran is visiting scholar at the Indian Institute of Statistics in Calcutta.
1957 Political Economy of Growth is published.
1960 Baran travels to Cuba with Paul M. Sweezy and Leo Huberman. Suffers heart attack in December, 1960.
1962 Baran makes major trip to Europe, the Soviet Union and Iran.
1963 Baran travels to Latin America, with lectures in Mexico, Chile, Argentina, Uruguay and Brazil
1964-03-27 Baran dies of massive heart attack while visiting his friend Leo Lowenthal for dinner in San Francisco.
1964-04 Monopoly Capital is published.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of correspondence, writings and audio recordings of Paul A. Baran.
Economics -- Study and teaching.; Economics -- United States -- Studying and Teaching.; Philosophy, Marxist.; Economics; Marxism; Sweezy, Paul M. (Paul Marlor); Baran, Paul A.; Thompson, Elsa Knight; Landau, Saul; Marcuse, Herbert; Brody, Richard A.
- Audio recordings, 1958-1963
  - What sort of revolution?, 1960-11-25; 2 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - On the Cuban invasion, 1960-04-20; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - U.S. policy towards China, 1958-10-18; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    McWilliams, Chan; Parsons, Clandes Mok; Baran, Paul A.
  - Paul A. Baran in Los Angeles, 1961-03-09; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - The work of Paul Baran, undated; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Marcuse, Herbert; Abramovitz, Moses
  - In the last analysis; Talk on affairs in Cuba after the Bay of Pigs invasion, 1961-05-04; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - In the last analysis; Analysis of American foreign policy under John Foster Dulles, 1963-05-24; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Panel discussion on Cuba, 1962-10-24; 1 optical disc(s) (cd) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Scope and Contents
    Panel discussion on the political and economic developments in Cuba following the revolution. They also discuss the implications fo the Cuban Missile Crisis.
    Landau, Saul; Thompson, Elsa Knight; Baran, Paul A.; Brody, Richard A.
- Biographical
- Correspondence, 1949-1964
  - Huberman, Leo, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Sweezy, Paul M. (Paul Marlor), 1910-2004., 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1-20)
  - Various
- Photographs, 3 computer file(s)
- Writing, circa 1930-1964
  - German writing translations, 1930-1933
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH_2017_292
  - General Correspondence, 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ccorrespondence with publishers, 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Maurice Dobb, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notes on "Festschrift" (Commemorative volume) for Maurice Dobb, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - PAB's critique of Abe Bergson, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with copy editor Jack Rackliffe, mainly re: Political Economy of Growth (PEoG), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence with Herbert Marcuse, 1948-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence with Andre Gunder Frank, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence with Oscar Lange, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence with The Nation, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oxford trip, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes and articles, 1942-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondnence with RAND Corporation, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Model, Roland, Stone, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes from Federal Reserve Bank, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Transcript of MR Associates lecture by PAB re: Soviet Party Congress, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Book review of "A Charter for World Trade," by Claire Wilcox, NYTimes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Book review of "Saving U.S. Capitalism," by Seymour Harris, NYTimes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Book review of "Spirit of Postwar Russia," by R. Schlesinger, Pol. Sci. Qrtrly., 1949 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Copies of book reviews in s 17 and 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Draft of article either by Paul Sweezy or PAB (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings and correspondence re: PAB's situation at Stanford, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Dobbs, Sweezy, and J. Rackliffe comments on PEoG, circa 1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Paul Sweezy and Joan Robinson on PEoG (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Reviews of PEoG (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Clippings (for research) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Business Week article on PAB, PMS, Huberman: "Viewing U.S. Economy with a Marxist Glass", 1963 Apr 13 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Lecture notes on history of economic thought, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes for Econ 120, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Back Examinations, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Unpublished interview with PAB October, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Notes and Lecture Transcript on Marxism and Psychoanalysis, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Transcript of Stanford Lecture, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Undated article on Nazi Economy, written in German, probably, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Articles published in German, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Unpublished German manuscripts prior to 1933, German Radio broadcast transcripts (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unknown letter to PAB re: manuscript entitled "Dennoch Marxismus," Polish writings (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bibliography and proposed collection (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Biographical material, circa 1951 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Intellectual and personal development, personal statement, biographical material, circa 1951 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Guggenheim application, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Personal statement, USSBS certificate, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - USSBS German occupation reports, interviews with German personnel, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - PAB Will, disposition of his library, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Manuscript re Social Democratic Party of Germany (SPD) (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Unpublished manuscript, circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Economic Progress and the Economic Surplus, manuscript plus commentary and letters, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Review by PAB and E.J. Hobsbawm of Rostow's "Stages of Economic Growth," manuscript and notes, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence incl. letter to Prime Minister Nehru, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous writings (drafts for his proposed journal "American Economist."), circa 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous writings/correspondence, incl. transcript of panel discussion re Cuba on KPFA 1962, 1948-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Academic credential documents, 1926-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Civil Service, OSS, OPA Documents, UNRRA Appointment to Poland (PAB could not take job, no passport), 1942-1948 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Office of Price Administration Paper, alleged to have been plagiarized by Otto Nathan, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Planning for Full Employment (with Lloyd Metzler); Remarks on USSR Economy, 1944-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - John Henderson's material on distribution of labor force, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Outline for book on socialism, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - First draft of "National Economic Planning.", circa 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Materials and Correspondence re: "National Economic Planning.", 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Polish Volumes (Kalecki-Lange Festschrift): "Notes on Imperialism," "Economics of Two World", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Article Notes, reprint of article, "New Trends in Russian Economic Thinking.", 1944-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Manuscript for "Foreign Investment: Trap or Opportunity,", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Manuscript for "The American Dilemma,", 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Notes on "Eighth Lecture" on Planned Economy, interview re: Cuba, Miscellaneous notes, circa 1963-1960 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Proposal for "American Economist,", 1946 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Tributes to PAB, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Files Pertaining to Passport Application (letters, affidavits, personal statement) (Box 3)
  - The Scientific-Industrial Revolution (pamphlet supplied by PAB under contract to investment bank Model-Roland-Stone, written by Paul Sweezy). (Box 4)
  - Latin American Trip (travel documents, clippings), 1963 (Box 4)
  - Stanford clippings/letters, circa 1961-1963 (Box 4)
  - Trip Receipts, 1953 (Box 4)
  - India (appointment at Indian Institute of Statistics, Calcutta): Letter to Nehru, other documents, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Misc. Manuscripts submitted to PAB and Sweezy (Box 4)
  - Drafts for Monopoly Capital: (Box 4)
  - QoS (2) ms and carbon (Box 4)
  - Ch. 12 with Jack Rackliffe Notes (Box 4)
  - Ch. 8 (Box 4)
  - Ch. 11 (Box 4)
  - Model, Roland Stone issues (PAB's monthly submissions to Model, Roland and Stone, circa 1950s (Box 4)
  - Lecture poster, 1928 (Box 5)